

LUIS SARMIENTO

Economist

As an experienced professional, I have developed substantial expertise in applied econometrics, energy modeling, and agent-based models. My research focuses on critical issues such as the sub-clinical effects of air pollution (productivity, well-being), city policies to decrease environmental externalities, the energy transition, and climate change.

Contact

egthinspace =
egt

gsaabogado@gmail.com



www.luissarmiento.com



luis-sarmiento-eco

Education

Doctor In Economics (SCL)

Berlin Institute of Technology 2017-2020 Berlin, Germany

M.S. in Economics & Mng.

Humboldt University of Berlin 2014-2016 Berlin, Germany

B.S International Business

University of Lasalle Bajio 2007-2012 Leon, Mexico

Software

R (R-Studio)

Quarto

Teamwork

Meeting deadlines

Critical thinking

Experience

Environmental Scientist
 European Institute on Economics
 and the Environment. Milan, IT.

Sep 2022 - Present

- Applied econometrics and causal inference.
- Design of micro-economic agent-based models.
- Scientific support to institutional activities.
- Mentoring of junior scholars.
- Study the relationship between digitalization and the environment.
- Post-Doc
 European Institute on Economics
 and the Environment, Milan, IT.

Sep 2020 - Sep 2022

- Applied econometrics and causal inference.
- scientific support to institutional activities.
- Study the relationship between digitalization and the environment

Research Associate

German Institute of Economic Research (DIW Berlin). Berlin. DE

Apr 2017 - Sep 2020

- Publication of scientific articles on energy and environmental economics.
- Research on the effects of air pollution and air pollution control policies on productivity, health, and wellbeing.
- Research Associate

Hertie School of Governance

Nov 2019 - Aug 2020

- Study the relationship between daylight savings and transit patterns.
- Business Executive

Banco del Bajio SA

Sep 2012 - Sep 2015

• Financial advice to small and midium-sized companies

Teaching

Environmental Economics and Policy
Winter 2023 (Upcoming)

University of Bologna

Environmental Economics and Policy
Spring 2023

University of Bologna

 Applied Econometrics for Energy and Environmental Economics
 (2020)

Summer (2020)

Berlin Intitute of Technology

 Applied Econometrics for Energy and Environmental Economics
 Summer (2019)

Berlin Intitute of Technology

Languages

Spanish

••••

English Italian

German



Latest Conferences

ICEE World ConferenceCagliari, IT. Spring 2023

Napoli, IT. Winter 2023

EAERE Annual Conference Rimini, IT. Summer 2022

Mannheim Conference on Energy & the Environment
Manheim, DE. Summer 2022

 Berlin School of Economics Workshop on Environmental Policies and Equity
 Berlin, DE. Spring 2022

References

Massimo Tavoni - RFF-CMCC:EIEE Director - massimo.tavoni@eiee.org

Christian von Hirshhausen - TU Berlin Professor - cvh@wip.tu-berlin.de

Juan Rosellon - CIDE Mexico Professor - juan.rosellon@cide.edu

Claudia Kemfert - DIW Berlin Professor - sekretariat-evu@diw.de

Publications

Sarmiento, Luis (2023)

The Nonlinear Effects of Pollution on Crime: Evidence from Mexico City and New York.

Environmental Research - Health 1(2), p.021001

Sarmiento, Luis (2021)

<u>Air Pollution and the Productivity of High-Skill Labor:</u> Evidence from Court Hearings

Scandinavian Journal of Economics 124: 301-332

Sarmiento, Luis, et al. (2021)

Mexico and US Power Systems Under Variations in Natural Gas Prices

Energy Policy, 151, 113378

Giarola, Sara, et al. (2021)

<u>The Role of Energy Storage in the Uptake of Renewable Energy: A Model Comparison Approach</u>

Energy Policy, 151, 112159

Gabela, J.G.F. and Sarmiento, L. (2020)
The Effects of the 2013 Floods on Germany's Road
Freight Traffic

Transportation Research Part D, S.1022774

Sarmiento, Luis, et al. (2021)
 Analysing Scenarios for the Integration of Renewable
 Energy Sources in the Mexican Energy System
 Energies, 12.17, 3270

Under Review

Luis Sarmiento, Nicole Wägner, and Aleksandar Zaklan Effectiveness, Spillovers, and Well-Being Effects of Driving R&R

K&R

Journal of Public Economics

Luis Sarmiento, Raul Gutierrez, and Juan Rosellon
The Effect of Changing Marginal Cost to Physical Order
Dispatch in the Power Sector

R&F

Economics of Energy and Environmental Policy

Luis Sarmiento and Adam Nowakowski

<u>Air Pollution and Court Decisions: Evidence from Ten Million Penal Cases in India</u>

R&R

Environmental and Resource Economics

Luis Sarmiento, et al.

Make Sure the Kids Are OK: Indirect Effects of Air Pollution on Well-Being

Under Rewiew

Nature Sustainability

Luis Sarmiento & Yeong-Jae Kim
 The Air Quality Effects of Uber

Under Review

Journal of Environmental Economics and Management